Guide to the Joseph Jones collection of papers relating to Indians of Tennessee,1846-1889
Jones, Joseph collection of papers relating to Indians of Tennessee,1846-1889
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Joseph Jones collection of papers relating to Indians of Tennessee, 1846-1889 1867-1868.
9152
Joseph, Jones 1833-1896.
.8 cubic feet.
Correspondence, manuscripts, publications, drawings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection focus is mainly on the Indians of Tennessee and Jones' work Explorations of the aboriginal remains of Tennessee or Antiquities in Tennessee. Covers Indian burial practices, archaeological digs, items found, and other information about Indian antiquities. Includes Mounted pages from Jones' book on notebook sheets with handwritten notes, probably a proof. A handwritten manuscript for the book, bound in a notebook with the hand written title "Explorations of the antiquities of Tennessee by Joseph Jones 1867-1868", with notes and correspondence interspersed. Page numbers do not correspond, but text does match in parts. Original watercolors and other illustrations, used for plates in the book, showing, skeletons, pipes, jewelry, and other artifacts. Correspondence to and from John Wesley Powell, the Bureau of Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution, Edwin Kenneth Burnett, William Porcher Miles, Alpheus Hyatt, A.C. Love, and others. Also included are newspaper clippings, maps, booklets, and other notes made by Jones.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Dr. Joseph Jones was a professor at the Medical Department of the University of Louisiana, later called the Tulane University School of Medicine. Before his appointment he served as surgeon in the Confederate States Army. He was involved with several scientific and historical societies and had an interest in studying archaeological research on Indian mounds.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection focus is mainly on the Indians of Tennessee and Jones' work Explorations of the aboriginal remains of Tennessee or Antiquities in Tennessee. Covers Indian burial practices, archaeological digs, items found, and other information about Indian antiquities. Includes Mounted pages from Jones' book on notebook sheets with handwritten notes, probably a proof. A handwritten manuscript for the book, bound in a notebook with the hand written title "Explorations of the antiquities of Tennessee by Joseph Jones 1867-1868", with notes and correspondence interspersed. Page numbers do not correspond, but text does match in parts. Original watercolors and other illustrations, used for plates in the book, showing, skeletons, pipes, jewelry, and other artifacts. Correspondence to and from John Wesley Powell, the Bureau of Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution, Edwin Kenneth Burnett, William Porcher Miles, Alpheus Hyatt, A.C. Love, and others. Also included are newspaper clippings, maps, booklets, and other notes made by Jones.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Jones, Joseph,1833-1896.; Burnett, Edwin Kenneth.; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902.; Miles, William Porcher, 1822-1899.; Powell, John Wesley, 1834-1902.; Huntington Free Library.; Louisiana State Museum.; Smithsonian Institution.Bureau of Ethnology.
Subjects:
Indians of North America.; Indians of North America--Jewelry.; Indians of North America--Funeral customs and rites.; Indians of North America--Tennessee--Antiquities.; Mounds--Tennessee.; Calumets.; Houma Indians.; Natchez Indians.
Places:
Cumberland River Valley (Ky. and Tenn.); Harpeth River (Tenn.); Nashville (Tenn.); Tennessee--Antiquities.; Williamson County (Tenn.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Box list included.
CONTAINER LIST
- Box 1
  - Mounted pages from Explorations of the Aboriginal Remains of Tennessee, onto notebook sheets. Antiquities in Tennessee. Joseph Jones, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Handwritten title for mounted pages 128-145; Title does not correspond to book headings: "V. Works of Art: Weapons of War: Jars and Pottery of the Aborigines of North America" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Handwritten title for mounted pages 13-35; Title does not correspond to book headings: "VI. Modes of Burial and Burial Customs of the Aborigines of America" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4 handwritten letters; 2 news articles; 2 collections of handwritten notes.
    - Addressee: Mr. E. K. Burnett. Correspondent: Elizabeth Mepham, December 14 ???? (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Addressee: Joseph Jones Correspondent: Mr. Mepham from M.S. Mepham & Bro, St. Louis, December 19, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Addressee: Mrs. H. Haushier, 726 So. 12th Saginaw, Mich. Contents are in Japanese: 1 page (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Addressee: Joseph Jones M.D. Correspondent: J.W. Powell, director Smithsonian Institution, Bureau of Ethnology, Washington, DC. regarding a shell ornament, Figure 29, and 30, from p.60 of Antiquities of Tennessee, Vol. XXII: 1 page, January 29, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones Correspondent: A.C. Love, Darrow, La. "relating to skeleton found with metal bracelets Houmas Indian, La.": 1 page, May 8, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones Correspondent: Wm. [Porcher] Miles, Houmas Plantation regarding Dr. A.C. Love's correspondence about a silver medal, dated 1727, and the remains of an Indian burying ground. Enclosed is a sketch of the front and back view of the medal: 2 pages, May 9,1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News Articles
    - From: The Daily Picayune New Orleans The Mound Builders Contents regarding the Natchez Indians and the findings of Dr. Joseph Jones: 5 pages., June 22, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From: New Orleans, Novemb[... ] Title: Stone Weapons. Observations on Spears and Arrow Heads. Contents regarding Egyptian arts studied by Jos. Jones, M.D., LL.D: 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hand Written Notes
    - Title: "Architecture of the Aborigines of North America" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Title: "Measurements of skulls in private collection of Joseph Jones, M.D., LL.D.5' Contents regarding 39 skulls, none noted as American Indian: 10 pages (8 handwritten, 2 blank) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten Notes; including 28 mounted woodcut prints of images onto notebook sheets, most images are from Explorations of the Aboriginal Remains of Tennessee
    - Title (p.2): "Catalogue of the Archaeological Collection of Joseph Jones, M.D. 156 Washington Avenue Corner of Camp Street New Orleans Louisiana" New Orleans, Louisiana Joseph Jones, M.D. Contents are regarding (p.3): "The antiquities described in this archaeological catalogue state chiefly to North Central and South America; but are illustrated also by works of art, derived from Europe, Africa, and Asia. Many of the implements of war, and the emblems of religious worship illustrating the arts of the ancient pre-historic (anti- Columbian) races of North America were taken form the aboriginal [...] and mounds with my own hands. All the objects described in this catalogue, were either obtained during my explorations and [...], or were directly purchased from their original discoverer and owner. In these instances I have given to the objects these names which best described their origin use [...]", September 6th, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, photographs, watercolors.
    - Mounted sketches, photographs, and watercolors onto 24 notebook sheets; most are original images of woodcut prints from Explorations of the Aboriginal Remains of Tennessee. Title of each notebook sheet: 'Woodcuts" (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mounted sketches, photographs, and watercolors onto 13 notebook sheets; most are original images of woodcut prints from Explorations of the Aboriginal Remains of Tennessee. Title of each notebook sheet: "Plates" 5 unmounted watercolors. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Box 2
  - Bound cloth text of handwritten notes, with inserted various letters and mounted photographic plates. Explorations of the Antiquities of Tennessee, by Joseph Jones, M.D., 1867-1868. "August 1866 Joseph Jones, M.D., New York" Contents Regarding: "Outline of explorations of the Antiquities of Tennessee and more especially of the Cumberland Valley, 1867-1868, by Joseph Jones, M.D. Illustrated with 22 Plates and One Hundred and Seventy-Four Figures. Nashville, Tennessee, 1868"
  - Plates, Photographic credit given to C.C. Giers, Nashville, Tennessee for all 23 black and white photograph plates:
    Plate 1: "Stone Idol. Discovered in Knox Co. near Straw[berry] Plains in [Aolston] River, in a cave [...] p. 2/3
    Plate 1: same as above, given again. p. 270/271
    Plate 2: "Figure 2: Side view of preceding stone idol. [...]" p. 272/273
    Plate 3: "Figure 3: Male stone idol, from valley of Cumberland River, Carroll County of sandstone." "Figure 4: Female stone idol from middle Tennessee, carved out of sand stone. Full face view"; p.274/275
    Plate 4: "Figures 5 & 6: Side view of preceding stone idols. [...]"; p. 276/277
    Plate 5: "Figures 7 & 8: Indian idols, females, comprised of clay and crushed river shells"; p. 278/279
    Plate 6: "Figures 9 & 10: Side view of preceding images. Showing the peculiar Aztec features of the black idol, and [...]"; p.280/281
    Plate 7: Figures 11, 12, & 13. cTigure 11: Idol from Middle Tennessee, comprised of red clay, and solid [...]." cTigure [12]: Female image, black and comprised of black clay and river shells, -hollow [...]." "Figure 13: Mexican Idol, from Temple of Chilula Mexico"; p.284/285
    Plate 8: Figures 14 & 15. "Figure 14: The head of the young man in Fig. 14 is that of my pupil JohnH. Monton." "Figure 15: Cranium of Princess of the Sun, from Sacred Mound on banks of Cumberland opposite Nashville"; p. 284/285
    Plate 9: "Tigure 16: Cranium Preistess of the Sun. Side view- Sacred mound from banks of Cumberland River opposite Nashville"; p. 286/287
    Plate 10: 'Tigures 17-20: Crania from stone graves, middle Tennessee, valley of Cumberland and tributaries"; p.288/289
    Plate 11: "Figures 21-28: Crania from stone graves, middle Tennessee, valley of Cumberland and tributaries"; p.290/291
    Plate 12: "Figures 29-33: Crania from stone graves, Valley of Cumberland and Harper"; p.292/293
    Plate 13: '"Figures 34-45: Ornaments from stone graves, middle Tennessee"; p.293/294
    Plate 14: "Figures 43-45: Diseased bones from stone graves of middle Tennessee, supposed to be results of syphilis"; p.294/295
    Plate 15: Figures 46-52: "Figure 46: Sea conch from stone grave, sacred mound, valley of Cumberland, opposite Nashville. [...]" "Figure 47: Vase, compound of yellow clay, and crushed shells, from stone grave near Franklin, Tenn." "Figure 48: Antique Vase from sacred mound, opposite Nashville." "Figures 49-53-54: Indian bones of upper jaw and face showing fine [...], prominent nose and c." "Figure 50: Indian bone of old Indian, from stone mound on [...] place." cTigure 51: Lower jaw, young Indian boy" cTigure 52: Lower jaw of old Indian, sacred mound, Cumberland River, opposite Nashville"; p.298/299
    Plate 16: "Figure 55: Sacred vase, from stone grave on banks of Big Harper, from mound in ancient fortification, 21/2 miles above Franklin, Tennessee, compound of yellow clay and crushed shells, [...]"; p.300/301
    Plate 17: "Figure 56: Bottom of sacred vase, figured in Plate 16, showing diversion of bottom into three portions"; p.302/303
    Plate 18: "Figures 57-61: Antique vases from stone graves, middle Tennessee" "Figure 57: Vase in shape of frog, from stone grave, Old Town, Big Harper" "Figure 58: Small black vase, with [...] on sides- stone graves, Colonel Overtons" "Figure 59: Vase representing head of Mexican hog, from stone grave, Old Town" "Figure 60: Vase representing frog, or some aquatic animal" "Figure 61: Black vase or water vessel with head of wolf, Cumberland Valley, near Nashville"; p.304/305
    Plate 19: "Figures 62-72: Antique vases from stone graves, middle Tennessee" "Figure 70: Clay cover for pots- used also for rubbing and pounding corn and paint"; p.305/306
    Plate 20: 'Tigures 73-101: Warlike implements of aborigines of Tennessee" "Figures 73- 99: Arrow heads, javelins, spearheads, scalping knives" 'Tigure 100: Stone hatchet, compound of green chloritic slate" "Figure 101: Stone hatchet, from sacred mound, Cumberland valley, opposite Nashville. Compound of green chloritic slate"; p.308/309
    Plate 21: Figures 102-114: "Figures 102-104: [Biconcan] discs, fashioned onto [...] and beautifully polished" Figure "106: Half of a stone bead" Figures "107-111: Fashioned of clay to crushed shells and appearantly employed to close the mouths of vessels and to crush corn" Figure "108: Pipe in shape of a [quale], with [bird] in back and hole for stem in tail. Widely cut out of sand-stone" Figure "109: Common Indian pipe. Compound of yellow clay" Figure "110: formed of green [rarigatent] serpentine" Figure "113: Magnificent pipe of peace {Calamet}. Cut onto of soft reddish green stone. Represents a South American bird? Parrot or Paraquite" Figure "114: Round stone formed of beautifiil pudding stone, the compound [of] pebbles of different colors, yellow, red, and black, forms a beautiful mosaic. Used in games"; p.310/311
  - Correspondence inserted into text:
    Newark, Ohio: November 14, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Jones; 2 pages; p.20/21
    Jones, Charles: New York, Oct. 9, 1868; Addressee: Jos. Jones; 3 pages; p. 22/23
    [Humes, W.L.W.]: Knoxville, Tenn., Aug. 27, '68; Addressee: Mrs. M.R. [Goff]; 1 page; p.26/27
    Arthedge[...], Mary: Nashville, August 15; 2 pages; p.28/29
    Addressee: Joseph Jones; 2 pages; p.28/29
    Addressee: My Dear Madam; 10 pages bound by string; poor condition; p. 30/31
    Botefor, J.D.; Fremont, [...] Co. Ohio, November 20, '68; Addressee: J. Jones, M.D.; 2 pages; p. 35
    [Hustias], L.G.D.; Chicago, Oct. 26, 1868; Addressee: Dear Sir; Impressed insignia on first page: 'Superfine AIP Co.'; 2 pages; p.36/37
    Hyatt, Alpheus; Salem, MA, Nov. 13, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; Letterhead: 'American Naturalist [...] published by the Peabody Museum of Science'; 1 page; p.38
    Byrd, Harvey L.; Baltimore, Nov. 10th, 1868; Addressee: Prof. Joseph Jones; Letterhead: 'Harvey L. Bryd, M. D. [...]'; 1 page; p.38/39
    Jones, Joseph; Nashville, Tennessee, Oct. 21, 1868; Addressee: Smithsonian Institution, Washington; 1 page; p.46/47
    Perdue, Chas. A.; Grinnell, Iowa, Nov. 16, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Jos. Jones; Letterhead: cIowa College'; 1 page; p.48/49
    [Snodgrass], [Joes.]; Sparto, Nov. 9, '68; Addressee: Dr. Jones: 1 page; p.50/51
    Gardenhin, E. L., J. Barnes; Livingston, Tenn., Oct. 18, 1868; Addressee: Joseph Jones, M.D.; 2 pages; p.74/75
    [Snodgrass], [Joseph]; Sparta, Oct. 16, 1858; 2 pages, (1 blank); p.76/77
    Thomas, W. S.; Manchester, Perm., Oct. 9,1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p.114/115
    Thomas, Wm. S.; Manchester, Penn., Oct. 20, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 114/115
    Hughes, At; West Harpeth, May 20, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 122/123
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., May 28, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 122/123
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, May 31st, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 2 pages; p. 122/123
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., June 4, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 122/123
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., June 5, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 122/123
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., Sept. 19,1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 128/129
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., Sept. 22,1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 3 pages; p. 128/129
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., Sept. 25, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 2 pages; p. 128/129
    [Montoz], John H.; Franklin, Tenn., Sept. 28,1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 2 pages; p. 128/129
    Anderson, J. M.; [Dechud]. Tenn., Oct. 19, 1868; Addressee: Dr. Joseph Jones; 1 page; p. 128/129
    [Montoz], John H.; Addressee: Dear Doctor; 3 pages (1 blank, 1 sketch of mound at [De'Graffrousuds]); p. 128/129
    Dunlap, R. E., John H. Dunlap; Contents: cIn the Spring of 1845 Mr. Hartsfield ploughed up an idol or statue made of stone about 8 miles North of Paris Tennessee [...]'; 1 page; p.210/211
    Dunlap, R.E.; April 14, 1846; Contents: Stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield; 1 page; p.210/211
    Harris, Wm. R.; April 14, 1846; Contents: Confirmation of statement made by R. E. Dunlap, about stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield; 1 page; p.210/211
    Brown, [H.], Clerk of Henry Circuit Court; April 21, 1846; Contents: Confirmation of statement made by R E. Dunlap, about stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield; 1 page; p.210/211
    Williamson, [...] B.; Contents: Confirmation of statement made by R. E. Dunlap, about stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield; 1 page; p.210/211
    [Frazieur], C, Clerk; Henry County, Paris, Tennessee, April 14, 1846; Contents: Stone idol found by 'Andrew Hartsfield7 and "bought by Ripley and Dunlap5; 1 page; p.210/211
    [Ges.], Janus H.; Carroll County, Tennessee; May 8, 1846; Contents: 'Statement of R. E. Dunlap, esqr. of Paris, Tennessee, in reference to mound wall, reservoir and other signs of antiquity5; 1 page; p.210/211
    Dunlap, R. E., R. A. Williams, John H. Warren, et al.; Henry County, Tennessee, April 14, 1846; Contents: Stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield, and its use; 1 page; p.210/211
    Troost, G., State Geologist of the State of Tennessee; Nashville, May 18, 1846; Contents: Stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield; 1 page; p.210/211
    Whites, S. H. M.; Charleston, East Tenn., Oct. 19, 1868; Addressee: Dear Dr.; Impressed insignia: 'Congress 5; 1 page; p.214/215
    Conigworth, R. R., Rec(ording) Sec(retary); New Orleans, August 19, 1869; Letterhead: 'New Orleans Academy of Science-1853'; Contents: Jan. 11, 1858, Extract from minutes, about limestone vase deposited by Mr. P. H. Shipwith found in a mound near Tallahassee River in Lafayette County, northern Mississippi; 1 page; p.266/267
    Stot[eg], Ja.; March 18, 1858; Addressee: Mr. M. N. Fogg; 6 pages bound by string; Entitled and crossed out: "Of the First People of America"; p.32/33
  - Newspaper articles inserted into text:
    Wilson, J. N.; "Pioneer Papers, No. 25. Mounds Near Newark"; print; 9 columns; p.20/22/24
    "The Dim Ages. Nashville. The Site of an Ancient and Populous City"; print; 3 columns; p.30
    "The Chicago Historical Society collection of pamphlets [...]"; print; 1 page; p.36
    "Early Discoveries in America. Mr. Rafn on the First Expeditions of The Northmen"; print; 2 columns; p.40
    "The Name of God in Forty Languages"; print; 1 column; p.42
    "Workmen excavating a cellar in Monroe County, Indiana, [...]; print; 1 column; p.52
    McWhirter, S. R; Franklin, Tenn., October 16, 1868; The Weekly Review. "Antiquities of the Cumberland, Charleston, East Tenn., October 18,1868"; Contents: Stone idol found by Mr. Hartsfield north of Paris, Tennessee; print; 2 columns; p.213
    Booklet: Jones Jr., Charles C; New York, March 7, 1868; "Ancient Tumuli on the Savannah River"; print; 8 pages, 1 map; p.24/25
  - Notes:
    "The figures of the Cross has been found in Mexico, and a [...];" handwritten; 4 pages; p.30/31
    Jones, Joseph; August 16,18[..]6; "Preface to the Explorations of the Antiquities of Tennessee"; handwritten; 1 page; p.30/31
    U.S. Sanitary Commission, The Smithsonian Institution; 1868; Contents: archival receipts; print and handwritten; 2 pages; p.44/45
    [Ma...] 15, 1891; (Contents: notes written in blue pencil); handwritten; 1 page; p.50/51
    "Natchez Indians. Accounts of Father Le Petit. New Orleans. July 12, 1730"; handwritten; 7 pages; p.58/59
    Maury, Tennessee; ccNotes on "Parishes' Mound"; Impressed insignia: 'Congress'; handwritten; 1 page; p.60/61
    Sept. 20, 1869; "William Fellows. Examined for life insurance"; handwritten; 1 page; p.88/89
    "Large oblong mound, half a mile from [...]; handwritten; 1 page; p.114/115
    Maury, Matt F.; Williamson County, Tennessee, Sept. 18, 1868; "Slate of Tennessee, WmSon County"; handwritten; 1 page (notes and map); p 118/119
    Maury, Matt F.; Williamson County, Tennessee, Sept. 18,1868; "Slate of Tennessee, Williamson County"; handwritten; 1 page (notes and map); p. 120/121
    [Montoz], John H.; April 5, 1868; "List of Indian Relics obtainence of Dr. Freeman for Dr. Joseph Jones"; handwritten; 1 page; p. 122/123
    "[...] of them one painted outside, and some inside"; handwritten; 1 page; p. 126/127
    "Notes on the mound at [De'Graflfrousuds], Williamson County, 3 miles above Franklin on Harpeth. Where the two vases bearing the 'Crosses and Crowns' were found"; handwritten; 4 pages (notes and maps); p. 128/129
    Maps of Harpeth River area; handwritten; 2 pages; p. 132/133